Guide to the Victor Bassett papers, 1877-1938 and undated RL.00087
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Victor Bassett papers
1888-1938 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bassett, Victor H.
RL.00087
2.0 Linear Feet 3 boxes
Physician, health officer, and librarian of the Georgia Medical Society; from Savannah. Collection contains public health information, including correspondence, health and mortality records, biographical information, genealogies, reports, and printed matter relating to the medical history and practice of medicine in Savannah. Also includes manuscript drafts from naturalist Walter J. Hoxie.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Victor Bassett Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1952.
Biographical Note
Excerpt from the Georgia Historical Society: "Dr. Victor Hugo Bassett was born on May 7, 1871, in Aledo, Illinois, son of Isaac Bassett. He received his medical training at the University of Wisconsin and Johns Hopkins University. Bassett came to Savannah, GA in 1908, as the city bacteriologist. In 1923, he became the City Health Officer, and County Health Officer in 1928. His research topics included diphtheria, typhoid fever, tetanus, and dysentery. He was also active in the Georgia Public Health Association, the American Public Health Association, and the Georgia Medical Society. Bassett died on November 3, 1938."
Collection Overview
Public health information, including correspondence, health and mortality records, biographical information, genealogies, reports, and printed matter. Most of the material relates to Bassett's work in public health and medical professional education efforts for Savannah and Chatham County, Georgia. Some topics addressed are school health examinations, nurses and midwives training, vaccination efforts, and milk pasteurization and licensing. There is also a significant amount of material acquired and assembled by Bassett as part of his role as librarian and medical historian for the Georgia Medical Society, including his research about the history of the medical profession in Savannah and Georgia from the colonial period through the late nineteenth century. Collection includes photoduplicates of original manuscripts and artifacts held in other repositories as well as Bassett's notes and drafts of biographical sketches about prominent Georgia physicians and families. Collection also contains Bassett's extensive lecture notes and laboratory notebooks from his medical training at the University of Wisconsin and University of Pennsylvania. Subjects covered include bacteriology, chemistry, infectious diseases, obstetrics, and gynecology.
Also held in this collection is a series of drafts by author Walter J. Hoxie, a naturalist and Girl Scout pioneer who also wrote columns for the Savannah Morning News and was an apparent family friend of the Bassetts. Most of the drafts appear to be unpublished folk stories or family stories; there are also bird-watching lists.
Public health -- Georgia -- Savannah -- History; Physicians -- Georgia -- Savannah; Malaria -- Georgia -- History; Medical education -- United States -- History; Georgia -- Genealogy; Savannah (Ga.) -- Social conditions; Smallpox vaccination -- United States -- History; Georgia -- Social conditions; Photographs; Bassett, Victor H.; University of Pennsylvania. School of Medicine -- History
- Personal materials, 1898-1938; undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Bassett's correspondence as well as miscellaneous ephemera and personal materials from his medical training and career. Some of the correspondence predates Bassett, but the majority of it relates to his work as a bacteriologist and health officer in the Savannah Health Department; his efforts to research medical history and biographical data for the Georgia Medical Society; and his participation in various medical and public health professional organizations in the early twentieth century. Additional materials relating specifically to the Savannah Health Department and the Georgia Medical Society are held in those series.
  - Correspondence, general, 1898-1938; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Jennie Johnson's medical (obstetrical) file, Johns Hopkins, 1902 (Box 1)
  - John Jarzinski's medical file and autopsy, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Clippings re: Bassett, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Clippings re: medical history, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Southern Medical Association pamphlets/ephemera, 1914-1937 (Box 1)
- Savannah Health Department materials, 1887-1938
  This series includes project files, reports, statistics, and publications related to Bassett's work as a bacteriologist, physician, and health officer for Savannah and its surrounding county, Chatham County. Some of the initiatives represented are vaccination; clean water; milk safety and inspections; infant/child health; prenatal healthcare; maternal healthcare; and Bassett's role in training for medical students, nurses, and midwives. This series also includes a selection of Bassett's reports on mortality and disease for the city of Savannah, divided by race.
  - City Water supply reports, 1887-1917 (Box 1)
  - Better Baby Contests, sponsored by the National Congress of Mothers and Parent Teachers Association, 1914 (Box 1)
    Contains correspondence and draft plans regarding Better Baby Contests, to be held at state fairs.
  - Monthly Health Bulletins and Records, 1923-1924; 1929-1932; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Contains statistics re: Savannah mortality and disease rates, subdivided by race.
  - Health Department notices and bulletins, 1924-1937 (Box 1)
  - Radio Healthgram scripts re: public health, 1930s (Box 1)
  - Georgia Board of Health/Board of Public Health bulletins and reports, 1929-1937 (Box 1)
  - Health examinations and reports for schools and children, 1930-1938 (Box 1)
  - Midwives and nurses: training, newsletters, correspondence, etc., 1935; undated (Box 1)
  - A Brief History of Public Health Work in Georgia, by M.E. Winchester (draft), 1929 (Box 1)
  - Milk Inspection reports, 1912 (Box 1)
    Clippings.
  - Bill amending Savannah's incorporation, 1925 (Box 1)
    Typescript.
  - Georgia Public Health Association membership, 1930 (Box 1)
  - National Malaria Committee membership, 1938 (Box 1)
- Georgia Medical Society, 1877-1936; undated
  Materials in this series relate to Bassett's work as a member and librarian for the Georgia Medical Society, including his work in building the library and its collections. There are also some overlapping materials from Bassett's Research Notes series, because he was involved in the GMS's efforts to prepare biographical sketches of early Georgia physicians and medical history.
  - Fee Bill of the Georgia Medical Society, 1877 (Box 1)
  - Officer elections/member lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: library collections, subscriptions, activities, 1915-1936 (Box 1)
  - Library Committee meeting minutes and reports, 1912-1914 (Box 1)
  - Shelving for library, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Book labels/bookplates for library collections, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of historical books, medical instruments, and artifacts, from GMS exhibit and library collection, undated (Box 1)
- Writings, 1912-1937; undated
  Bassett appears to have been a prolific author, and a small portion of his drafts and essays are in this series. Topics range from public health or medical issues and treatment to personal essays and genealogical research on various figures in Georgia medical history.
  - Anti-Typhoid Vaccination, 1912 May 28 (Box 1)
  - Diagnostic Value of Trachial Tug, undated (Box 1)
  - Health Work in a Seaport City, 1931 Apr. (Box 1)
    Published in Health News.
  - Essay honoring midwives Rosa Ridle and Margaret Rushing, 1937 (Box 1)
    Contains drafts as well as correspondence about the retirement plans of these midwives.
  - Intravenous Saline Infusion, undated (Box 1)
  - Lemuel Kollock biography draft, 1860; undated (Box 1)
    Includes Bassett's draft as well as research and correspondence about Kollack; contains one original letter from Kollock dating from 1860 as well as reproductions of other original documents.
  - Drafts of book review of "Medical Magic," by David Dietz, undated (Box 1)
  - Response to "Place of the Practicing Physician in a Public Health Program," paper by James Paullin, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Quantitative Relationship of Malarial Parasitism, with Special Reference to Microscopic Diagnosis, undated (Box 1)
  - Book review of "Significance of an Epidemic of Dengue," by Griffitts and Hanson, undated (Box 1)
  - Untitled drafts on Vaccination in Savannah, undated (Box 1)
  - Voices of the Past, 1937 (Box 1)
    Correspondence about reprints.
  - What present is suitable for a boy interested in natural history?, undated (Box 1)
- Research notes
  A range of materials from across Bassett's professional life are held in this series. Subjects are arranged alphabetically and include professional organizations; medical topics; public health issues; medical history, including genealogy for Georgia physicians; and other miscellaneous topics. Bassett's files include both his collected and composed notes as well as printed materials and typescript excerpts from other publications.
  - American Medical Association Library reprints, copies re: medical association history, undated (Box 1)
  - Experimental ground itch treatment photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Georgia-degreed physicians list, 1798-1930, prepared by Cecilia Mettler, A.M., undated (Box 1)
  - Georgia Medical Repository reprints, copies, undated (Box 1)
  - Johns Hopkins Hospital clippings, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Le Conte genealogy, undated (Box 1)
  - Notes from the Letters of James Habersham, in the Georgia Historical Society, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Macleod family notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Marriages of doctors in the 1800s, undated (Box 1)
  - Medical history notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Medical training/licensing notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Excerpts from the 4th Annual Meeting of Medical Society of the State of Georgia, 1853, undated (Box 1)
  - Milk/pasteurization, undated (Box 1)
    Includes publicity photographs of a model dairy farm in Wisconsin, undated.
  - Mortality records for City of Savannah, 1803-1806, notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Pathology, miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Plantation doctors, undated (Box 1)
  - Savannah Historical Research Association, undated (Box 1)
  - Savannah Library Association founding, undated (Box 1)
  - Remarks on the Sources and Qualities of Honey, by Paul Delacy Baker, 1858 (Box 1)
  - Typhoid, undated (Box 1)
    Includes a flyer for an auto-closing latrine designed to prevent flies and disease.
  - Research re: William R. Waring, J. J. Waring, and Frederick Waring, 1880s-1934 (Box 1)
    Includes copy of a diary from J.J. and Frederick Waring's travels in Europe, 1853-1855.
  - Yellow Fever epidemics, 1888-1897 (Box 1)
    Contains two original documents collected by Bassett: a certification of clearance for the ship Lizzie Heyer, sailing between Havana and Savannah, 1888, and a health certificate for Rebecka B. DuPont, 1888.
- Walter J. Hoxie, 1922-1934; undated
  This series includes unsorted, undated, untitled manuscript drafts that appear around the theme of "Granpa's Stories," written by Hoxie. There is also a small number of titled drafts on Seminoles, porcupines, and salamanders, as well as a published obituary for Hoxie.
  - Obituary and biographical essay, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Birdwatching notes, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Seminole customs and miscellaneous language notes, 1932; undated (Box 1)
  - Salamanders, undated (Box 1)
  - Porcupine Camp, undated (Box 1)
  - [Granpa's Stories] drafts, various, undated; 4 folders (Box 1, Box 2)
- Lecture notes, 1891-1903; undated
  Bassett's lecture notes, lab books, and other materials from his medical training at the University of Wisconsin, University of Pennsylvania, and Johns Hopkins University are held in this series. Some notes are bound by Bassett. Topics include infectious diseases, gynecology, obstetrics, bacteriology, and other medical subjects.
  - Bound notes re: anatomy/physiology taught by Ray Murlin, University of Pennsylvania, 1891-1892 (Box 2)
  - Notebooks re: bacteriology and chemistry, University of Wisconsin, 1896-1899; undated (Box 2)
  - Notebooks re: bacteriology, water analysis, University of Wisconsin, 1890s (Box 2)
  - Notes re: infectious diseases (including lab book), 1898-1902 (Box 2)
  - Notes re: medicine/medical topics, miscellaneous, 1901 (Box 2)
  - Notes re: malaria, blood/blood diseases, treatments, miscellaneous topics, 1901-1903 (Box 2)
  - Notes re: obstetrics, lectures by Dr. Williams, 1901-1902 (Box 3)
  - Notes re: obstetrics, 1902; undated (Box 3)
  - Notes re: gynecology, 1902-1903 (Box 3)